hello and welcome to today's video in
today's video i'm gonna be going over
how we could make a safe load system uh
using json within unity the reason i'm
using json and not something like the
binary i'm not using something like the
uh binary formatter is because microsoft
actually recommends not using it they
say it's not safe and it should just not
be used now for your game maybe that's
not a big issue you know it only becomes
an issue if you're sharing save files
but if your game gets big and players
want to upload their save files on you
know steam workshop or just on different
sharing sites there's no way to make
those save files safe or check whether
they're safe so someone could upload a
dodgy save file a player would
unknowingly download it and then that
could execute some code on their machine
so the binary format is out so i'm using
json you could use something like xml if
you wanted there are ways to encrypt it
um our current save when you look at a
json file it's fully readable here
players can access this file and then
they can change the data in it so they
could do uh
you know the x position of the player is
20.22222
so it's not safe in that regards
players will be able to modify it so
then you'd have to look into sort of
encryption i'm not going to cover that
here because at the end of the day if
you're going to be making a single
player game does it really matter if
they change the the data on their save
file if that's how they get their fund
them you know even games like valheim
for example they use json you can go in
you can change your server settings you
can change your player settings and
that's a multiplayer game so you know
it's going to be dependent on everyone's
kind of preference i don't mind players
may not access their data i'm only
probably ever going to make single
player games so yeah that's fine and if
i did want to go into multiplayer games
then you could look into encryption so
just before we jump straight into it i'm
doing this video as a standalone you can
follow this video if you've not watched
any other videos however this is also
going to be a prerequisite video for the
save load system on my inventory series
so if you've been following along with
the inventory tutorial series and you
want to know how to save your
inventories we're gonna have to watch
this one and then in the next video in
that inventory series we'll adapt the
code that we've written here to actually
make it apply to our inventory system
and if you didn't know i had an
inventory system tutorial series then
why not watch it i think it's quite good
people seem to be enjoying it i'll put a
little card up here to link you to the
first video in that series and just one
last thing before we get started i would
highly recommend this uh official unity
video after you've watched this one and
it talks about serialization in unity
and kind of what it all means and how it
sort of works under the hood but with
that said let's just get straight into
this video okay so here i am in the new
unity hub i'm gonna start a new project
up here um if you don't have the new
unity hub you can either you know update
it to get it
or
i'm gonna be using the first person core
template if you don't have this
what you'll need to do is uh just create
a new um urp project and then get this
starter assets first person character
controller um from unity it's free
and you can get this kind of downloaded
and installed um
but if i pick the first person core it's
just gonna do all of that for me so um
let's call this save
load tutorial
and then come over to create project so
while that's loading and doing its thing
i just want to point out some stuff
about script serialization other than
what i discussed kind of in the start of
the video so
here's the unity um docs for
serialization just to go over it a
little bit more so serialization is the
automatic process of transforming data
structures or object stakes into a
format that unity can store and
reconstruct later now we can save this
out in a certain format for example
binary json xml but there are some
different rules about serialization um
there are some like uh stuff that you
can't serialize so for example we've got
um
these are the rules to be able to
serialize something so a field has to be
either public or private with the
serialized field attribute and it can't
be static const or read-only and there
are certain simple field types that can
be serialized so for example
custom structs with the serializable
attribute which is something we may use
um we've got references to objects that
derive from unityengine.object the
primitive data types such as ins floats
doubles bool strings
enums and certain unity built-in types
so vector 2 vector 3 vector 4
et cetera you can um
you can serialize them out and there are
certain containers that can be
serialized such as arrays and lists
and by default dictionaries can't be
serialized and if we want to serialize a
custom class it has to have the
serializable attribute it can't be
abstract it can't be static um and it's
not generic though it can inherit from a
generic class
so these are just some stuff to kind of
you know keep in mind
when we when you're working on a safe
load system
um but so this is all loaded now if i
hit play we can just see where we are
like what's going on
um
here's the play window so it's just a
first person controller i can run and
jump i'm just a little capsule
um
you know we can do something a little
bit more interesting now such as uh
keeping track of the player's position
and use that to save load etc so i'm
just going to
get rid of the readme
and let's just dock
that up there
okay so let's go over to our scripts
let's go i'm going to go over to the
assets folder
and come over into our scripts these are
the scripts that came with the template
i'm just going to right click create um
a folder and let's call this the save
load system so the first thing i'm going
to do is i'm going to make a class i'm
going to call this class save data so
let's just create a c-sharp script and
we'll name this um save data
okay so here's our um save data script
let's just get this nice and big
so the first thing we know is that for
our custom classes to be uh serializable
they have to be marked as such so we can
outside of the class we need to put
system
open a square bracket and do system dot
siri elizabel
like that
and then we can get rid of mono behavior
because we don't need it to be we don't
need the save data class to be attached
to an object and then let's bring that
and get rid of all of this
and ryder is telling me
so let's move this to the um
save load namespace
so we've got namespace
save load system
save loads system
let's rename this folder
to
save
load system
and then
open up
our save data
and rename that to save load system okay
so
this is our save data for now i'm just
gonna put a public int
in here and we'll just call this um
index and let's set this to one so this
is serializable it's it says in rider
unless you know that it's serializable
i'm also going to have a serialized um
field
and i'll do a private
uh let's do a float and i'll just call
this um my float so we can equal this to
5.85
0.8 f why not
so this is now our save
data um
save data is very specific to your game
so i'm putting this in just so we've got
something to work with but you know your
game is going to be different if are you
doing a top-down 2d game with a big
inventory system then you're going to
need to store you know the chests what's
in the chests etc if you're just doing
um
you know if you've got a custom map
level editor you're going to need to
save a completely different set of data
so you know this there's no you know
there's no save button there's no one
click just save the state of the game
you have to decide
ahead of time what you want to be saved
such as your player's position their
inventory their current health you know
all of the interactions they've had keep
track of npcs and what they've been up
to but with that said let's just get
this set up and work in and i'll show a
bit more of a practical example of how
we could maybe um use this to keep track
of some stuff to do with the player this
is our save data and i'm going to come
back over to
unity and in our save load system i'm
going to right-click create c-sharp
script and let's call this one the save
game manager and then let's open up our
save game manager and again this wants
to be in the safe load namespace
let's get rid of this
so here let's get rid of all of this as
well i'm gonna zoom this back in i'm
gonna make this a public static
class and here i'm gonna have a public
static
uh save data
called um current
save
data
and we can set this equal to a new
um
save data
the reason i'm doing this is now we can
keep track of this uh save data we can
access it from sort of anywhere
um sorry and that should be a capital c
so we've got our static save data
current save data so now we need a way
to be able to save this save data to
file so for that i'm going to be using
um json the json format so there's some
stuff we can do and just to get this
working so i'm going to make a public
static
bull method and i'm just going to call
this save
and we can um
make this a new method
and let's just return true for now
so to save um
later out it's actually very simple so
um we're gonna need somewhere to save it
which is a directory on the computer um
so i'm gonna make a public
const
string
and we can call this the directory
and we can set this equal to a new
string and i'm going to
save in a directory just called
save data this could be you know save
games
this could be saves save games
you can name this whatever you want and
i'm going to make a public
string um and we can call this the file
name
and i'm just going to do save game dot
sav
you can
again you can make anything up here that
you want you could have
um you know you could just save it as a
text file you could do um dot save dot
sav like it doesn't really matter you
can make up your own extension
um
but we just need to have that as a
string
alternatively if you want to be able to
save out stuff with different names um
you could pass in a string and do
file name as a
string here and then when you save it
out you could use this file name that
you've passed in as opposed to a
hard-coded one but i'm just going to use
the hard-coded one for simplicity stake
so let's get rid of that so the first
thing i need to do is i need to make a
um a temporary string called uh
for directory and this is gonna be equal
to the application dot persistent data
path
uh plus our directory which is uh this
up here now application dot persistent
data path is uh it's a set place by
unity and it works cross-platform and
it's different no matter like which
platform you're in if you want to know
exactly where um your stuff's gonna be
saved you can do
dot persistent
data path unity you can see here that on
the windows store apps it's going to be
saved in um app data local packages
uh on the windows editor and standalone
player it's going to go into our local
low um folder which is our company
followed by the company and the product
name
and for linux it's you know it's it's
different
you know this is just one kind of call
you can make and then it's cross
platform so you're not having to like
hard code the actual directory for
everything
so for me this is going to go into my
local low folder um and then it's just
going to tag on forward slash save data
forward slash if we come up to edit um
project settings
and here we've got our save load
tutorial that's the product name so
that'd be the name of your game um
company name let's just put this as uh
damn puffs
so looking at this my save file on
windows is going to go to
app data local low
downpass
which is here and then product name
which is here so it'll be dampos save
load tutorial
and then it'll be in um a save data
folder within this persistent path so
now we've got this full like sort of
path as a string and we can just say if
the directory
dot exists
so if this directory doesn't exist
okay i've noticed an issue here um
i've got this string called directory
and then i'm trying to get um
but then directory is also a class so
that's why it's getting confused so
let's just rename this to save directory
there we go that's fixed and we need to
be using the system.io um namespace and
yeah so if this directory doesn't exist
this dir
then we just want to um make that
directory so we can do directory.create
directory
and then pass into
so when we call save it's going to
check what the the full directory
including this this folder that we're
going to create and if that doesn't
exist then we're going to make that
folder so that's the first thing that we
need to do
and then
we're going to come down here and we're
going to say string
json is equal to and i'm going to use
json utility
dot to json i'm going to pass in
our current save data
and we're going to put in true here for
pretty print which will make it um
without this it puts all on one line and
it looks gross
so we want to have pretty print to true
and then we can just call file dot
write all text
and here we're going to pass in the
directory because this is the path that
we're going to write all of the texts to
so we need to do the
du which is our full path
plus our file name
so this here is where if you took in a
string um as a parameter of this you
you'd put the string here as opposed to
using the hard-coded file name
and and the text that we're going to
write out is our json string
which is this here
and then just to make this easier so i
can open the folder i like to do um gui
utility dot um
system copy buffer is equal to our
plus the um
file
name
the reason for this is that when i call
save it's just going to copy the path to
my clipboard and i can just paste it
into windows explorer instead of trying
to navigate to
the local low folder because it's a bit
of a pain in the butt
you know for now that's our save system
done it's going to save out here and
we're returning true
um just to say that it was successful
and
you may want to put in some you know
other checks and it could return false
if something's going on for example if
the scenes load in
you can put some different checks in
um but this is just so we know that the
save has been completed
successfully so
we now need a way to call our save
function so um let's go over to
unity again
i'm going to right click
create uh empty and let's just call this
um
our save tester so back in unity i'm
going to make um just a button that will
allow us to just click the button and
then we can save the game so if i come
up to
if i right click sorry in the project
do ui
and just make a new button
let's just call this the save game
button
and then
let's find this in the scene
in 2d mode
oh
and i'm going to make the canvas um
screen space overlay that's fine but i
want it to
scale with the screen size and then i'm
just going to put in
by 1080
and then let's get our button
and i'm going to move the button uh just
down here
uh
oh let's just scale it up slightly
and for our text let's do um
best fit just to make it
a bit bigger and then i can just just
put in save
um
while we're here i'm just going to make
a load button as well
load
game button
which we can't use just at the minute
but we will be able to use it um
in a second
so let's go to our load text and just
put load here now on our canvas i'm
going to make a new script i'm going to
call it just a save game tester
now you might want to call this the save
game manager or
wait we've already called that the save
game manager but you know what i mean
like
so this save game tester script you know
this may be your game manager script you
can plug this in kind of
this functionality into whichever script
it kind of makes sense to do so on your
own game um but for me i'm just gonna
here make a public void
save game uh function
and when this function's called it's
gonna access our save game
uh
manager
and it's just gonna save the game
now if i come back over to our save game
button
and on click we want to
find our save game tester script and
just call the save game function
let's just add our public void
um load game
function here and we can do save game
manager
dot uh
load which we haven't actually made yet
so let's just um
load game here
so with our load game button come down
to on click drag in our canvas and then
just hook in
the load game function which again
doesn't do anything at the minute but it
will do
and
so if i come back over to our game
let's just set this to
1920 by 1080
so if we hit play now
you know we can walk around and i can
hit the save button and our game is
going to save so if i hit save
that work
i can't tell if that button actually
pressed
let's just disable our um player
capsule for now
um i don't want it to capture the mouse
if i hit save there we go the button is
saved
and because we
put the system.copybuffer in
oh actually this needs to just be the
directory it doesn't need to be the file
name um that is my mistake
so
let's just save that and reload and
let's do that again so if i hit play
and hit save so that's going to have
copied the
um
to our clipboard so i can just come up
here and paste that in you can see that
it's gone into app data local load down
pass save load tutorial in our save data
folder and we've got our save game file
here which is a dot sav
file if you want to get to this folder
without copying it to your buffer um on
windows anyway you can
press the windows key type in run
type app data surrounded by the
percentage signs click ok
and then you've got to come back out to
app data go into local low
find your company name your project name
and then the actual folder so
you know it's just quicker to be able to
just paste that in and hit enter now
let's open up our save game
and here's our save game so we've got uh
index which is one and my float which is
equal to 5.8 f
it's added some extra stuff onto the end
of it
but you know that's fine um
so let's just come back out of here so
now we can put some different stuff in
our save data as well so we can do
for example a public bull
just call this uh our bull sets to true
do a public um
vector
three
called
our vector
and then maybe set this to
um a new vector 3 of 0
10 99
which again is marked as serializable so
let's just close this down
hit play
hit save
make sure we close this go back over to
our project
and open up our save game so now we can
see that we've got uh index of one my
flow our bull our vector
so that's how you save out data so how
would we load this so if i um
stop the game let's work on loading the
data now
if i come over to our same game save
game manager
so what we need to do now is um
we need to
make a public static
void load
and let's just do save game uh load game
and let's just rename this to um
save game
just so we're a bit more explicit about
what we're loading and saving
and so we've got load game and we can do
string
full
path and this is again equal to our
application dot persistent data path
um plus our
save directory
and then plus
our
file name
so this is the exact file that we want
to be able to load
um we're not loading the directory we're
loading in the save data so we need to
have the file name included again if
you've put a custom file name in here
you'll have to check that custom file
name in load game and pass that in as
well
so we now need to make um
just a
some save
data
called um
temp data
or sets equal to a new save data
and we can say if file dot exists
at our full path so if we have a save
game here
then we want to um recreate our json we
need to load in our json string
so here just as we saved it out we want
to
recreate it as a json file so we can do
string json
is equal to file dot read all text
at our full path
and then we need to convert this json
back into some save data
so we can say
uh
temp data is equal to json utility
dot
dot from
json and we want to
open up some angle brackets and this is
going to be the type of save data
and we'll pass in our json path so
we're getting our json string back into
the program and then we're using the
json utility to turn that string back
into our class and our custom class of
save data
and if the file doesn't exist
let's just debug dot log error
save
file does not exist
and then at the end after all that we
can do
current save data is equal to our temp
data
so let's just check that's working so in
our save game tester
what i'm going to do is i'm going to do
save game
manager
dot and then let's
get the
current save data
and let's change the index to 10
and then let's save the game so let's
just make sure that's working
so our current data um
index is one so let's just make sure
that's closed
so let's hit play
and then let's hit save
and let's check our saved aim save game
data now so index is 10 so we've changed
to that
now let's check the loading is working
so if i do um here in our load game what
we can do is do save game manager
dot
load game
so before i load the game let's change
the index again to
um
20 this time
and then let's load the game and now
let's debug
dot log
the save game manager dot current save
data dot index
so what should happen here is we're
gonna we've changed our index to um
10 and then we've saved the game
and then we're gonna
change it again when we load it to 20
we're going to load the game and then
print it and if our load games work in
it'll print back out the 10 that we've
saved and if it isn't working it'll
print out 20 because uh it won't work so
we've changed it to 20. so let's just
check
let's just check that so again we'll hit
play
let's come over to the console so let's
save our file out
and let's just check so it's definitely
index 10.
now let's load our game
and you can see here that it's debug.log
10.
so even though we set it to 20
after we've loaded the game it's
actually 10.
so that shows that our index um our save
game system's working
okay so this is all working so how can
we make this a bit more game related not
just a bunch of just useless junk
let's get rid of all of that and just
save our file so in our scripts folder
in our save load system
uh oh yeah and then because that's
uh
because i've deleted all that data we
just need to get rid of this
so let's make a custom struct now of
some player information so
if i
come over to our player capsule from
this starter asset and just um
re-enable that
okay so i'm going to add a new script to
our player and let's just call this um
player save data
so in our player save data script um
outside of the class
i'm going to make a new struct called
public
i'll do public struct and we'll call
this the player data
and we need to mark our struct as system
dot serializable
and now we can define what we care about
on our player so this is where you'd
save out their you know their current
inventory system uh their position so we
can do a public vector
three
um player
position
we could do um public
int
player
her current health
and you know you can do
lots of different stuff in here you can
again it's very specific to whatever
your game is that you're working on um
so i'm just gonna
uh i'll just leave it at player position
and current health they're two good sort
of test cases
and it's now back in our save data class
i'm going to make a reference to public
um
player data
called um
player data and set this equal to some
new play data
so now in our player save data um
i'm gonna here
make private player data
and do um my
data
and set this equal to some new player
data now in our update function we can
say my data dot player position is equal
to transform dot position
uh we could maybe do as well a public
quaternion
player rotation
and then we can do
my data dot player rotation is equal to
transform dot rotation
so every frame i'm going to be keeping
track of our um
player position so this is going to be
like a constantly saving thing you know
you might not want to do this on every
frame you may want to set up your own
kind of custom event so every um
you know every 30 seconds
it logs the play position
if you've got an auto save system that's
a good way of doing that or like a
checkpoint system and when a player
passes through a checkpoint
then you'll only then you'll need to
update this but i'm just going to do it
every frame
and i'm going to say that if um
oh and then let's do current health as
well my data
dot
current health
is equal to current health
which is going to be
a public void i don't sorry public int
and
current health
let's just default this to 10.
say if keyboard
dot current dot um
r key
dot was pressed this frame so this is
using unity's new input system uh which
is enabled by default with the first
person
template if you're doing this in your
own game and you're not using the new
input system um
you know you'll just do like
input.getkeydown keycode r
but this is using the new input system
so that's how you do that so if the
keyboard.current.r key was pressed this
frame
then let's call our savegame manager
uh let's actually make a new um
we're gonna have to do a couple of
things so we'll do save game manager dot
uh current oh
dot current save data dot player data is
equal to my data
and then we'll do save game manager
dot
save
game
so every frame is going to be updating
the player position player rotation and
the current health and then when i press
r
we're going to set our save games
current saved game
current save data
player data which is this struct we're
going to set that to my data which is
this version that we're keeping up to
date every frame
something else that you could do is you
know instead of doing my data you could
do the save game dot current save game
dot play data and update that directly
um
i think this is a good way of just
keeping track of this
keeping it all in one script and then
updating the save game manager when just
when needed
um so we can set our player data
equal to my data
and then i'm gonna do if
keyboard
dot current dot um i'll just do the t
key three uh the reason i'm using random
keys is because i don't know what's um
you know like wised space and all that
setup already and
i think r t should be fine to use so if
current dot t key dot was pressed to
this frame then we're going to do save
game manager dot load game
and then we can say my data
is equal to the um
save game manager dot current save data
dot player data
and then from that i can say
transform.position
is equal to mydata.position
i can do
transform.rotation is equal to
mydata.playerrotation
oh
player rotation and then i can say
current health is equal to my data dot
current health
and rider is telling me to cache
my transform
so i'll do that um so let's go over to
unity now um and i don't actually need
these save game buttons because i can't
use them
uh
when the capsule is activated so if i
hit play
so we're walking along we're updating
our position and let's select our player
capsule so you can see our position up
here
let's go
over here so
-15 on the x uh below one on the y
minus one on the edge and we've got a
y rotation of 84.95
and our current health here is 10. so if
i hit the
r key
that's gonna have saved our game and it
will have copied the directory to the
path i'm already there open up save game
and we've got player data so player
position minus 15 just minus 15
y
um
zero point eight
minus one that's all good current health
equal to 10.
so if i now change our current health to
say five and then i
run over here
and i hit the t key
gonna load our game and reset our
player's position rotation and health so
do uh t
you can see it's loaded us back
and it's
put us
with -12 is that where i was
[Music]
okay that was a bit of a pain in the ass
um okay so
there was a bit of an issue uh with our
function the problem was that with the
first person controller template uh this
first person control the script so
somewhere in this script we're setting
the position uh with the character
controller i think it's here this
controller.move obviously that's that's
the bit that's moving the player
and this is called every frame
now what was happening is that we'd hit
the load button
and then it would set our position to my
player.position this was all loading
fine but then immediately on the next
frame there was a bit of like a hangover
kind of somewhere in the script um and
it'd move you back to the frame that you
just were and you'd have to press load a
few times
for you to be the one that got called
last and actually
for the save data to overwrite the
actual data
so
one solution for this is i've got a
reference to our first person shooter
controller which is our first person
controller here and i'm going to get
that component in the awake function and
then
what i'm going to do is go
keyboard.current.t
key was pressed this frame i'm going to
disable the controller i'm going to do
all of our jazz and set the transform
etc and then
after 0.25 seconds i'm going to
re-enable the controller which will
basically stop this
overwriting what we're doing here
so while the game is saving none of this
is going to be happening and then once
it's finished saving we just got a
little bit of a buffer to re-enable this
another way of doing this would be in
our save game manager
uh have some you know public static uh
unity
actions
like on save game
sorry on load
game start
and then we could have onload game
[Music]
finish
we could call on games unload game
starting here
after it's finished loading we can do
onloadgame.finish
and invoke that and then in all of the
scripts that need to
know when a game's loading
i'm gonna get rid of this this was just
for me trying to fix it that because
that didn't seem to work for some reason
so in all of our scripts here we could
subscribe to our on
enable we could subscribe to our save
game manager um
and detect once the game started loading
you know do some logic based on that and
then once the game is finished loading
re-enable anything that we need to like
actually enable
um but for our case here
um this works just fine so let's go back
over to unity
and let's see it not work now and be a
pain in my book
so
i'm going to come over here i'm going to
save the game
by pressing r
we can look at the save data file
so we've got current health 10 our
rotation and position that's all the
same the rotations change because
obviously i looked down
um
but that's all
groovy
now if i come back over to the game i'm
going to change our
health to three i'm gonna run over here
let's come in here and then i'm gonna
press
t on the keyboard
and that teleports us back and we can
carry on moving and we've got our all of
our health back let's you know go up so
we've got 20 health now
i'm going to come over here
i'm going to save it looking up this
staircase so press r to save the game
i'm going to run back out here press t
and there we go we're looking up the
staircase and we've got our health back
uh our health stayed at 20. if i set
this to 10 and then press t and load it
there you go looking up the stairs got
our 20 health back so from this point on
it's kind of up to you what you want to
do and what you what you class is
needing to save um you know
this is just a good kind of example of
that we've got our player
save data and like i said you could have
your inventory system
um you know the amount of gold that the
players got instead of the health the
unlocks that they've got
you know you could have a public
bull
um double
jump
acquired
uh this could be
you know and then you can get your
double jump and then you'd keep track of
that here
um you can do whatever you whatever you
need to do keep track of completely up
to you but yeah if you've got any
questions do let me know in the comment
section below if you want the project
file for this you can play around with
it and have a look at how i've set stuff
up that will be available over on
patreon.com forward slash dan pass if
you've got any issues with the project
or any questions that you want clarified
let me know in the comments below or
head over to the discord server which is
linked in the description and i should
be able to help you there but in the
meantime thanks for watching and i'll
catch you in the next one bye